<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Bodhinaya Meditation Group, Amaravati Buddhist Monastery, Hemel Hempstead</title>
    <description>We are a group of lay Buddhists and people interested in Buddhism who meet to meditate and discuss Buddhist practice at Amaravati Buddhist Monastery on Wednesday evenings at 7.30pm to 9.20pm. We welcome anyone who is interested in Buddhism, including those who are new to Buddhism or new to Amaravati. Our discussions focus on understanding the Buddhist teachings and how we can apply them in our lives. We meet in the Bodhinyana Hall.</description>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0)</copyright>
    <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/readingsfeed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 16:03:26 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 16:03:26 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    <managingEditor>martin.evans350@ntlworld.com (Martin Evans) </managingEditor>
    <webMaster>helencalderon@gmail.com (Helen Calderon)</webMaster>
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>What is the foundation of lay Buddhist practice?</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-refuges---the-vehicle-for-lay-practice&quot;&gt;The three refuges - the vehicle for lay practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Marvellous, venerable sir! It is as if a person were to turn face upwards what is upside down, or to uncover the concealed, or to point the way to one who is lost or to carry a lamp in the darkness, thinking, ‘Those who have eyes will see,’ so has the Dhamma been set forth in many ways by the Blessed One. We go to the Buddha for refuge, to the Dhamma for refuge, and to the Sangha for refuge. May the Blessed One regard us as lay followers who have gone for refuge for life, from today.”  (extract from the Kalama Sutta)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on a translation from the Pali by Soma Thera.  Anguttara Nikaya, Mahavagga, Sutta No. 65&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a standard text found in many Suttas, where lay people hearing the discourse take the three refuges as a commitment to becoming a lay Buddhist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-we-taking-refuge-in&quot;&gt;What are we taking refuge in?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-buddha&quot;&gt;The Buddha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not taking refuge in the historical Buddha of the past but in his enlightenment as an experience which is available now, in the present.  Clearly this requires a conviction that the Buddha realised enlightenment in the past, but more so, the conviction that this can be realised by us in the present – the Buddha is here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dhamma&quot;&gt;The Dhamma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not taking refuge in the Buddha’s teachings as something sacred to be believed in, but a path we can use to realise reality – to see the way things are. And the path is to be realised here and now, not put on the shelf for when we have time, or for some future life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-sangha&quot;&gt;The Sangha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not taking refuge in the community of monks and nuns, but those who can point the way.  The Buddha walks with us as a guide in the form of the Sangha – but Sangha who walk beside us and help guide us towards the goal are those who have realised or at least glimpsed the truth, whether they are monastic or lay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-four-similes&quot;&gt;The four similes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth reflecting on what the four similes mean.  They are all about revealing something which is hidden from us by our misperception, but is already there.  All we need is the truth uncovering, or light to see with, the way pointing out, or in the case of something upturned, it turning over so we see it as it really is.
MRE 23 Mar 15&lt;/p&gt;

]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/03/25/what-is-the-foundation-of-lay-buddhist-practice-part-one/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/03/25/what-is-the-foundation-of-lay-buddhist-practice-part-one/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Martin Evans</dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The worldly winds</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The eight worldly winds are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pleasure and pain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;praise and blame&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fame and disrepute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gain and loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are pairs of opposites: one we are attracted to, the other repulsed by. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pleasure, fame, praise and gain all make us feel good, like the stock market on an upward swing. We may get a big head with fame, lose sight of our responsibilities with pleasure, rely on external validation with praise, or feel exceedingly comfortable with gain. These things we all desire and delude our clear minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, we can be carried away by their opposites. We can become absorbed by our pain, our esteem can suffer from disrepute, feel excessively guilty with too much blame, and loss can leave with us with endless grief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being swept away by any of these eight winds causes emotional instability, stirring things up they cloud our clarity. Just set a course sailing down the middle, not directly against the wind nor with it, and respond with the tiller to keep things straight. Accept each wind without following it, realising its conditions are impermanent. Then when the wind changes direction you can respond appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/03/11/worldly-winds/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/03/11/worldly-winds/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator></dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Watching the breath (Anapanasti)</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Anapanasati&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a way of concentrating your mind on your breath, so whether you are an expert at it already or whether you have given it up as a lost cause, there is always a time to watch the breath. This is an opportunity for developing ‘samadhi’ (concentration) through mustering all your attention just on the sensation of breathing. So at this time use your full commitment to that one point for the length of an inhalation, and the length of an exhalation. You are not trying to do it for, say, fifteen minutes, because you would never succeed at that, if that were your designated span of time for one-pointed concentration. So use this span of an inhalation and an exhalation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/buddhasfeet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Buddha&#39;s feet&quot; /&gt;
Now the success of this depends on your patience rather than on your will-power, because the mind does wander and we always have to patiently go back to the breath. When we’re aware that the mind wanders off, we note what it is: it may be because we tend to just put in a lot of energy at first and then not sustain it, making too much effort without sustaining power. So we are using the length of an inhalation and the length of an exhalation in order to limit the effort to just this length of time within which to sustain attention. Put forth effort at the beginning of the exhalation to sustain it through that, through the exhalation to the end, and then again with the inhalation. Eventually it becomes even, and one is said to have ‘samadhi’ when it seems effortless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first it seems like a lot of effort, or that we can’t do it, because we aren’t used to doing this. Most minds have been trained to use associative thought. The mind has been trained by reading books and the like, to go from one word to the next, to have thoughts and concepts based on logic and reason. However, anapanasati is a different kind of training, where the object that we’re concentrating on is so simple that it’s not at all interesting on the intellectual level. So it’s not a matter of being interested in it, but of putting forth effort and using this natural function of the body as a point of concentration. The body breathes whether one is aware of it or not. It’s not like pranayama, where we’re developing power through the breath, but rather developing samadhi – concentration – and mindfulness through observing the breath, the normal breath, as it is right now. As with anything, this is something that we have to practise to be able to do; nobody has any problem understanding the theory, it’s in the continuous practice of it that people feel discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But note that very discouragement that comes from not being able to get the result that you want, because that’s the hindrance to the practice. Note that very feeling, recognise that, and then let it go. Go back to the breath again. Be aware of that point where you get fed up or feel aversion or impatience with it, recognise it, then let it go and go back to the breath again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anapanasati: literally, ‘mindfulness’ (sati) of the in and out breath. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/25/watching-the-breath/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/25/watching-the-breath/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Ajahn Sumedho</dc:creator>
        
        <dc:source>http://cdn.amaravati.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Mindfulness_-The-Path-to-the-Deathless-Ajahn-Sumedho.pdf</dc:source>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Loving kindness</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-buddhas-words-on-loving-kindness&quot;&gt;The Buddha’s words on Loving-kindness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Karaniya Metta Sutta)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Now let us chant the Buddha’s words on loving-kindness.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This is what should be done]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By one who is skilled in goodness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And who knows the path of peace:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let them be able and upright,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straightforward and gentle in speech,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humble and not conceited,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contented and easily satisfied,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unburdened with duties and frugal in their ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peaceful and calm, and wise and skillful,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not proud and demanding in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let them not do the slightest thing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That the wise would later reprove,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wishing: In gladness and in safety,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May all beings be at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever living beings there may be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether they are weak or strong, omitting none,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great or the mighty, medium, short, or small,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seen and the unseen,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those living near and far away,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those born and to be born,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May all beings be at ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let none deceive another&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or despise any being in any state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let none through anger or ill-will&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish harm upon another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as a mother protects with her life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her child, her only child,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a boundless heart&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should one cherish all living beings,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radiating kindness over the entire world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spreading upwards to the skies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And downwards to the depths,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outwards and unbounded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freed from hatred and ill-will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether standing or walking, seated or lying down,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free from drowsiness,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One should sustain this recollection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is said to be the sublime abiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not holding to fixed views,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pure-hearted one, having clarity of vision,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being freed from all sense-desires,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is not born again into this world.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/18/loving-kindness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/18/loving-kindness/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator></dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>How should we use the Dhamma?</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The Buddha called his teachings the Dhamma. If we grasp the Dhamma incorrectly it is a bit like grasping a snake – if we grasp it by the head it bites us, if we grasp it by the tail it bites us. We grasp it by the head if we are sceptical – we find fault with it straight away. But if we believe it, it is like grasping it by the tail. One day we will become disenchanted with Buddhism, so it bites us later. The right way to grasp the Dhamma is through investigation. That is like getting hold of the snake just behind the head. Now it cannot harm us – and it becomes useful - we can even extract the venom and use it as an antidote for suffering – in the same way we can use the Dhamma to extract insight. It is through insight or understanding that we bring suffering to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in order to use the Dhamma correctly, we need to find the middle way between sceptical doubt and blind faith – and that is through developing our own self confidence in investigating the Dhamma, and testing it out. There us a phrase, ‘meditative enquiry’, which I think describes this approach perfectly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-buddhas-charter-of-free-enquiry&quot;&gt;The Buddha’s charter of free enquiry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/an/an03/an03.065.than.html&quot;&gt;Kalama Sutta&lt;/a&gt; the Buddha gives some wonderful guidance about the importance of knowing for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Kalamas: ‘Don’t go by reports, by legends, by traditions, by scripture, by logical conjecture, by inference, by analogies, by agreement through pondering views, by probability, or by the thought, “This contemplative is our teacher.” When you know for yourselves that, “These qualities are unskillful; these qualities are blameworthy; these qualities are criticized by the wise; these qualities, when adopted &amp;amp; carried out, lead to harm &amp;amp; to suffering” — then you should abandon them.’ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Kalamas, ‘Don’t go by reports, by legends, by traditions, by scripture, by logical conjecture, by inference, by analogies, by agreement through pondering views, by probability, or by the thought, ‘This contemplative is our teacher.’ When you know for yourselves that, ‘These qualities are skillful; these qualities are blameless; these qualities are praised by the wise; these qualities, when adopted &amp;amp; carried out, lead to welfare &amp;amp; to happiness’ — then you should enter &amp;amp; remain in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;everything-is-uncertain&quot;&gt;Everything is uncertain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to remember Ajahn Chah’s advice, ‘everything is uncertain’. But even this advice we need to grasp correctly. Where can we go wrong? We need to keep questioning ourselves, ‘is it possible we are mistaken?’ Self belief is as bad as self doubt. Neither is the self confidence I am talking about. We need to grasp the Dhamma with meditative enquiry – a kind of scientific enquiry. It is an evidential approach. We try it out and look at the results. This is why we call it a gradual path. There is no short cut to enlightenment through belief – that just leads up a blind alley to disenchantment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-your-own-way&quot;&gt;Finding your own way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where does that self confidence come from? This is like asking, ‘Where is the origin of wisdom?’ We don’t need to know the answer. All we need to do is be grateful for what we have, and use it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MRE – 6 Feb 15&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/11/how-should-we-use-the-dhamma/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2015/02/11/how-should-we-use-the-dhamma/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Martin Evans</dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Buddha’s smile</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;When I was at school was told off for smiling. I was given a detention. And when I was in detention I was given another. I was still smiling. I was told to ‘wipe that smirk off my face’. I didn’t know it was wrong to smile until then. Most people love to see a smile. There is nothing more warming to the heart than to be met with a smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to look at the Buddha’s face. Can you see his smile? It is very subtle. Why is he smiling? Is he experiencing a blissful meditative state? Or is it the smile of someone who is experiencing nothing? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can think that the Buddha’s enlightenment is an escape from the world, an escape through meditation into a sublime state of existence. If we think that then we try to create this blissful state, through practicing some meditation technique, to develop concentration. But the Buddha rejected the path of concentration as leading to the ultimate goal in itself. He tried it and found it didn’t lead to the end of suffering. He didn’t deny the benefits of the concentrated mind, but he didn’t find it led him to the experience of the truth of the way things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we can think that it is a complete escape into nothingness or some sort of non-existence. Well, the Buddha was very clear that his enlightenment wasn’t of this world nor another. It wasn’t an escape of any sort. It was a release, a freedom, but not a rejection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is this smile? I think it is the experience of now. The end of seeking for anything other than the way it is right now. In our worldly thinking we could say ‘contentment with nothing’, because the currency of our experience is the past and the future. There is no experience of now in the grasping mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this word now is a better word than mindful or aware. How is it right now? This question brings us into the immediacy of awareness or mindfulness, whereas to think of being aware indicates something we are going to be in the future. In the future we will never be aware, if we are not aware in the now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the experience of laying down a burden. Doesn’t that bring on a smile? Ah, yes, I know how that feels. When I walked from Lands End to John O’Groats I learnt all about how it felt to lay down my burden at the end of the day. The funny thing is, all we seek is contentment and that laying down of the burden is all it takes, that letting go into the way things are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is the smile of compassion. Isn’t that a mystery, where this compassion comes from when there is no one trying to be compassionate. We think that we need to become compassionate. We don’t have the trust that compassion is the expression of our true nature. When this sense of me and mine dissolves, this delusion of self, then there is nothing hindering the expression of compassion. And, although compassion is feeling the suffering of others, nevertheless, here it is in the form of a smile. But it is a slightly sad smile isn’t it. A smile that embraces both happiness and suffering. Not an escape from the world, but a complete openness to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;isnt-it-wonderful-that-the-buddhas-smile-is-already-within-us-just-waiting-to-get-out&quot;&gt;Isn’t it wonderful, that the Buddha’s smile is already within us, just waiting to get out.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we meditate we should cultivate this smile, we need to gladden the heart. I don’t mean to become happy clappy people - Theravada Buddhism tends to appeal to people who like to take things seriously – but the right attitude to practice is a light heartedness. We shouldn’t make it into a struggle. This is how people so often approach it, through their conditioning. They are looking for something to make a struggle out of. When you tell them it is their nature to see, they don’t listen. They don’t trust in their own ability to see the truth because it can’t be like that, life has to be an endless struggle. So it is. It goes on and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow a meditation technique, it can be something to create a problem out of, rather than a stick to support you in your practice. It really doesn’t much matter what technique you use provided you have the right attitude to your practice. Certainly some techniques are more suited to certain temperaments. But the trouble is, what would be most helpful is generally the one we least want to do. This is certainly true of loving kindness (&lt;em&gt;metta&lt;/em&gt;). It is most beneficial to people of an angry temperament, but the people who really like doing it are those of a lustful temperament. (We all have these temperaments but one tends to predominate. Our challenge is to bring them into balance). That’s why it’s a good idea to think of giving yourself up to the practice, rather than cling to what you like. After you have tried it, then you can see for yourself whether it was beneficial or not. This willingness to be open to whatever is in the moment creates a pliant mind, which of wonderful benefit, far greater than whatever benefit you could get out of any meditation technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This attitude to practice, this gentle openness, this pliant mind, supports our development of awareness, of being in the now. It takes time, but you begin to realise what the value of a technique is in your meditation practice, and where the danger of it lies. The danger of a support, especially if it has been useful, is that we hold onto it when it’s time to let go. We have to abandon our attachment completely. So it is really good to take this on as a path of practice. I used to say, ‘if it’s let-go-able, let go of it’, and I used to test things out with this mantra. I used to investigate everything that came into the mind this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to test out my feelings, asking myself ‘who is feeling this way?’, and resting with the silence in the mind which followed. This is the practice of insight (vipassana). It doesn’t depend on any meditation technique; it is just a way of letting go of our attachment to me and mine, our grasping mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bearing-with-rather-than-doing-battle-with-the-mind&quot;&gt;Bearing with, rather than doing battle with the mind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are not trying to defeat the mind. We want to do battle with the mind because it is not how we want it to be. But we should change our attitude. We should cultivate kindness towards the thoughts that arise in our minds. Trying to get rid of thoughts or block them out, this is how we empower them. When we take no special interest in them they will leave of their own accord, in their own time. This willingness to bear with what arises in the mind requires the cultivation of boundless patience – what a wonderful quality to develop. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some thoughts are very sticky. The thoughts that hang around, these are the ones we most want to get rid of. They are the ones that have something to teach us. So we should listen to them, let them be our teachers. When we have learnt what we need to know they will not trouble us again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajahn Chah described it as inviting your guests into a room in which there is only one chair, and you are sitting on it. So your guests are welcome, but they can’t stay long because they have nowhere to sit. And, he said, when people are uncomfortable, they reveal themselves and you can see them for who they are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we should not do battle with our thoughts. Selecting those we like and dislike just traps us in our preferences, our conditioned world. It is not the way to see them as they are. The mind is a receptacle for thoughts. Thoughts arise and cease in it, that is the nature of the mind. Like people who come and go in your life. You have to welcome them all as friends, whether you like them or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mindfulness-is-the-practice-of-now&quot;&gt;Mindfulness is the practice of now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you are practicing mindfulness, this practice of now, you are aware of whatever arises in the moment. When thoughts arise, you keep them standing until they go away. This is how you should be with thoughts. You don’t sit down with a lustful thought, or an angry thought. Keep them standing until they reveal themselves and leave. But don’t despise thoughts, for if you do you will despise your mind. It is in the mind that insights arise. The mind is where we can reflect, where we can see things as they are. We have no better friend than our own mind. I have heard people say that what they want to do is stop the mind. But they are concentrating the mind over here to escape from what they don’t like over there. They are running away. They think there is somewhere they can hide. But they are trying to hide in their own house. Who are they hiding from? It is terribly sad because this body and mind is all they have in the world. What they need to stop is the grasping mind. This is where true happiness is found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the Buddha’s body. We abide in a body, it is what keeps us on the earth. It can give us a lot of pain. Physical pain helps remind us we are body bound. It brings us down to earth. It is a good place to focus the mind, and let go. The same with restlessness, these are our teachers. We should stay with them and learn. Don’t rush out of class before the teacher has finished the lesson. Look at this restlessness. It isn’t a problem, it is a wonderful teacher, but we have to develop the patience to stay with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we do this? Because it leads to freedom. When we know restlessness, we don’t need to run away from it anymore. When we stop running away the mind becomes completely at ease, with both the body and the mind, whatever the moment brings, in the moment, in the now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is where the transformation occurs, that turning outside of what has been for so long hidden inside. All our humanity, vulnerability and compassion that is folded within, turning outward to the world, like an opening flower. No wonder the Buddha smiles. But it is subtle isn’t it. It takes a little time to see that smile, and to discover it in our own practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-we-begin&quot;&gt;Where do we begin?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may need to develop many qualities we don’t yet possess. But more than anything, we need to develop that quality of trust. It is the trust in the path of practice and the confidence in our own natural reflective ability to understand this body and mind, to see things as they are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Buddha could see that there was this potential in us all, to be enlightened. But his smile is tempered with the sadness that so few of us realise it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My garden is full of fruit trees I planted 20 years ago. Every year I have enough fruit for everyone, I feel almost embarrassed I have to give so much away. All I have to do is wait for it to ripen, then gather it up. This is nature isn’t it. But look at all the gardens with no fruit in them. All the people who probably think, if they’d planted some trees, they would have fruit now. But they still don’t plant fruit trees. They probably think it isn’t worth it, that it takes too long before you get any fruit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Buddha said that one of the greatest blessings is to have done good actions in the past. We all live in a garden, it is our mind. We need to develop and train it, in morality, concentration and wisdom. What I am talking about is the confidence that if we plant and nurture our fruit trees, one day our fruit will ripen. The only way to have the fruit of past good action is do good actions now. We are very fortunate, we have this opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MRE – updated 06/02/15&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 16:50:47 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2014/10/07/the-buddhas-smile/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2014/10/07/the-buddhas-smile/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Martin Evans</dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Discourse on the hightest blessings (Mangala Sutta)</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;I heard these words of the Buddha at one time when the Lord was staying at Savatthi at Anathapindika’s Monastery in the Jeta Grove. Late at night, a Deva appeared whose light and beauty made the whole of Jeta Grove shine radiantly. After paying respects to the Buddha, the Deva asked him a question in the form of a verse: 
“Many gods and men are eager to know
What are the greatest blessings
Which bring about a peaceful and happy life.
Please, Tathagata, will you teach us?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is the Buddha’s answer):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• Not to be associated with the foolish ones,
To live in the company of wise people,
Honouring those who are worth honour—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To live in a good environment,
To have planted wholesome seeds,
And to realize that you are on the right path—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To have a chance to learn and grow,
To be skillful in your profession or craft,
Practicing precepts and loving speech—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To be able to serve and support your parents,
To cherish and love your family and
To have a vocation which brings you joy—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To live honestly, generous in giving,
To offer support to relatives and friends,
Living a life of blameless conduct—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To clearly avoid unwholesome actions,
Not caught by alcoholism or drugs,
To diligently walk on the path of good—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To be humble and polite in manner,
Grateful, content with a simple life,
Not missing the occasion to learn the Dharma—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To persevere and be open to change,
Make regular contact with monks and nuns,
And to fully participate in Dharma discussions—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To live diligently and attentively,
To perceive the Noble Truths,
And to realise Nibbana—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;• To live in the world
With mind and heart undisturbed,
With all sorrows ended, dwelling in peace—
This is the greatest blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The one who accomplishes this
Is unvanquished wherever they go,
Stable and free at any time—
Happiness lives within oneself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mangala Sutta,  Sutta Nipata 1,&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 16:50:47 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2014/04/07/discourse-on-the-highest-blessings-(mangala-sutta)/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2014/04/07/discourse-on-the-highest-blessings-(mangala-sutta)/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Thich Nhat Hanh</dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>&lt;i&gt;Parami&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ndash; perfections</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parami&lt;/em&gt; means &lt;em&gt;perfection&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;completeness&lt;/em&gt; of certain virtues which cultivate a way of purification while reaching a goal of enlightenment. The Buddha completed these ten perfection known as &lt;em&gt;dasa parami&lt;/em&gt; before his enlightenment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sumedho.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ajahn Sumedho and Ajahn Chah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dana-parami-generosity-giving-of-oneself&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dana parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: generosity, giving of oneself.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the beauty and joy of our humanity – being able to love, to share, to be generous; to give without caring whether anyone else knows or acknowleges it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sila-parami-virtue-morality&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sila parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: virtue, morality.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observing Buddhist precepts is a training; we don’t demand that we immediately become perfect. The precepts are guidelines; they help anchor us. They encourage restraint from unskilful actions of body, speech and mind. They uplift us towards that which is noble, good, kind and generous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nekkhamma-parami-renunciation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nekkhamma parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: renunciation.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way of spiritual life is a movement away from the distraction of attaining or acquiring. It is a relinquishing, a letting go. It simplifies our lives, freeing us from that which is unnecessary. There’s no judgement or rejection, it is pure mindfulness developing in the present moment – the only place Truth can be found&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;panna-parami-wisdom-insight&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panna parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: wisdom, insight.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living wisely means we observe our attachments, understand them, and let them go. And we don’t just attach to ideas that we should or shouldn’t be attached to things. Wisdom means we can recognise our own particular forms of pride and attachment to views and opinions, the material world, our teachers and the tradition to which we belong&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;viraiya-parami-effort-diligence&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viraiya parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: effort, diligence.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our practice involves a courageous effort to look deeply into things; not merely analysing our personality. We resolve to follow the path until we have profound understanding. Everything fits into the same pattern, the same law: all that arises ceases&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;khanti-parami-patience-tolerance&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Khanti parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: patience, tolerance.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient endurance is the foundation of my practice. We need to learn to endure, patiently and kindly, through the troughs of disillusionment, to stop reinforcing old cycles of habit. Then come to cessation – the silence and emptiness of the mind&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sacca-parami-truthfulness-honesty&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sacca parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: truthfulness, honesty.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
 &lt;em&gt;Sacca Parami&lt;/em&gt; – truthfulness – is perfected as a determined willingness to see things as they are in terms of Dhamma and not believe in or be intimidated by one’s own views, opinions and feelings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adhitthana-parami-determination-resolution&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adhitthana parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: determination, resolution.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice is voluntary; there is no compulsion. The energy required has to come from within – from our own hearts. Don’t expect someone else to enlighten you. Your effort can be useless if all you’re doing is rearranging your actions of body and mind so you become a Buddhist. That’s not liberation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metta-parami-loving-kindness&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metta parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: loving, kindness.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metta is kindness with awareness. It doesn’t mean we resign ourselves to mediocrity or to tyranny. It means that we don’t get caught in the old patterns of fear, depression, jealousy or resentment. When we stop dwelling in aversion for ourselves or others it is easier to bear with the vicissitudes of life&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upekkha-parami-equanimity-serenity&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Upekkha parami&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: equanimity, serenity.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we’re mindful, creativity is spontaneous – there’s no attachment to ideas and memories of self. There’s no one who loves or is loved; there’s no personal being that is created. Being mindful in this way, we find the real expression of kindness, compassion, joy and equanimity that is always fresh, always kind, patient and ever-forgiving of oneself and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajahn Sumedho - From the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forestsangha.org/assets/calendar/2011/forest-sangha-calendar-2011.pdf&quot;&gt;Amaravati calendar 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

]]></description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 15:50:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2013/11/13/parami-perfections/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2013/11/13/parami-perfections/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Ajahn Sumedho</dc:creator>
        
        <dc:source>http://forestsangha.org/assets/calendar/2011/forest-sangha-calendar-2011.pdf</dc:source>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Maha-parinibbana Sutta &amp;ndash; Relinquishing the Will to Live</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sangha came, indeed, to witness the greatest event in its history, and was keenly aware of it, especially since the Master had announced his Parinibbana three months ahead. The impression on the bhikkhus who flocked to him in large numbers as he was pressing northward was tremendous, and could not fail to be reflected vividly in the oral account. (The Buddhist canon was originally, as is well known, altogether oral.) Because of its particular import and abundance, this material was soon formed into one body; and so our sutta came to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this connection, it is hardly possible not to remember gratefully the Venerable Ananda. His share in the preservation of the Master’s word is paramount to any other bhikkhu’s, and his figure is inseparable from our texts. This was to become manifest for all time in the Maha-parinibbana Sutta, which is plainly unimaginable without him. For it is Ananda, and again Ananda, whom the Master addresses, having tested for twenty-five years his sure grasp and brilliant memory and also his indefatigable personal devotion. But Ananda too, here more than elsewhere, by his constant queries, worries, and amazements, becomes without intending it a central figure beside the Master himself, which undoubtedly increases the attractiveness of the text. Thus, then, Ananda, gentle and pleasant as his name, and yet almost throughout his career incurring the reproach of the brethren, was immortalized along with his beloved Master, and — as we may add — along with his strange position between praise and blame, assuming mystic character in the third chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third chapter, almost exclusively, is devoted to depicting the circumstances connected with the Master’s relinquishment of life, which is the dramatic culmination of events. It overwhelmingly drives home the purely metaphysical significance of the Parinibbana, or at least ought to do so. For the Buddha neither succumbed to his fatal illness nor did he give way to the appeal of Mara (which is identical with the non-appeal of Ananda), but sovereignly let go of existence at a timely hour, just as forty-five years earlier, on becoming fully enlightened, he had duly taken upon himself the wearisome task of teaching men. This fact is most thought-provoking, and consistently leads to the conclusion that by his Parinibbana, indeed, the Buddha bore the last and highest possible testimony to his Teaching, which permits of no lingering inclination to self-preservation and continuance, but on the contrary reaches the highest exultation ending it all. The Master’s Parinibbana is, therefore, the one sorrowful event in the history of Buddhism that turns out, in its true meaning, to be really the most blissful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Sister Vajira Ceylon, May 1961&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The third chapter: Relinquishing the Will to Live&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Blessed One&#39;s Prompting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Then the Blessed One, getting ready in the forenoon, took bowl and robe and went into Vesali for alms. After the alms round and meal, on his return, he spoke to the Venerable Ananda, saying: &quot;Take up a mat, Ananda, and let us spend the day at the Capala shrine.&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;So be it, Lord.&quot; And the Venerable Ananda took up a mat and followed behind the Blessed One, step by step.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt; And the Blessed One went to the Capala shrine and sat down on the seat prepared for him. And when the Venerable Ananda had seated himself at one side after he had respectfully saluted the Blessed One, the Lord said to him: &quot;Pleasant, Ananda, is Vesali; pleasant are the shrines of Udena, Gotamaka, Sattambaka, Bahuputta, Sarandada, and Capala.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;li&gt; And the Blessed One said: &quot;Whosoever, Ananda, has developed, practiced, employed, strengthened, maintained, scrutinized, and brought to perfection the four constituents of psychic power could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Tathagata, Ananda, has done so. Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
 But the Venerable Ananda was unable to grasp the plain suggestion, the significant prompting, given by the Blessed One. As though his mind was influenced by Mara, &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  he did not beseech the Blessed One: &quot;May the Blessed One remain, O Lord!. May the Happy One remain, O Lord, throughout the world-period, for the welfare and happiness of the multitude, out of compassion for the world, for the benefit, well being, and happiness of gods and men!&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
And when for a second and a third time the Blessed One repeated his words, the Venerable Ananda remained silent.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Then the Blessed One said to the Venerable Ananda: &quot;Go now, Ananda, and do as seems fit to you.&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Even so, O Lord.&quot; And the Venerable Ananda, rising from his seat, respectfully saluted the Blessed One, and keeping his right side towards him, took his seat under a tree some distance away.
&lt;/li&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Mara&#39;s Appeal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
And when the Venerable Ananda had gone away, Mara, the Evil One, approached the Blessed One. And standing at one side he spoke to the Blessed One, saying: &quot;Now, O Lord, let the Blessed One come to his final passing away; let the Happy One utterly pass away! The time has come for the Parinibbana of the Lord.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;For the Blessed One, O Lord, spoke these words to me: &#39;I shall not come to my final passing away, Evil One, until my bhikkhus and bhikkhunis, laymen and laywomen, have come to be true disciples — wise, well disciplined, apt and learned, preservers of the Dhamma, living according to the Dhamma, abiding by the appropriate conduct, and having learned the Master&#39;s word, are able to expound it, preach it, proclaim it, establish it, reveal it, explain it in detail, and make it clear; until, when adverse opinions arise, they shall be able to refute them thoroughly and well, and to preach this convincing and liberating Dhamma.&#39; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;

&quot;And now, O Lord, bhikkhus and bhikkhunis, laymen and laywomen, have become the Blessed One&#39;s disciples in just this way. So, O Lord, let the Blessed One come to his final passing away! The time has come for the Parinibbana of the Lord.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;For the Blessed One, O Lord, spoke these words to me: &#39;I shall not come to my final passing away, Evil One, until this holy life taught by me has become successful, prosperous, far-renowned, popular, and widespread, until it is well proclaimed among gods and men.&#39; And this too has come to pass in just this way. So, O Lord, let the Blessed One come to his final passing away, let the Happy One utterly pass away! The time has come for the Parinibbana of the Lord.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Blessed One Relinquishes His Will to Live&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;li&gt;When this was said, the Blessed One spoke to Mara, the Evil One, saying: &quot;Do not trouble yourself, Evil One. Before long the Parinibbana of the Tathagata will come about. Three months hence the Tathagata will utterly pass away.&quot;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And at the Capala shrine the Blessed One thus mindfully and clearly comprehending renounced his will to live on. And upon the Lord&#39;s renouncing his will to live on, there came a tremendous earthquake, dreadful and astonishing, and thunder rolled across the heavens. And the Blessed One beheld it with understanding, and made this solemn utterance:

&lt;blockquote&gt;What causes life, unbounded or confined &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
His process of becoming &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  &amp;ndash;  this the Sage
Renounces. With inward calm and joy he breaks,
As though a coat of mail, his own life&#39;s cause. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:26&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:26&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Then it came to the mind of the Venerable Ananda: &quot;Marvellous it is indeed, and most wonderful! The earth shakes mightily, tremendously! Dreadful and astonishing it is, how the thunders roll across the heavens! What could be the reason, what the cause, that so mighty an earthquake should arise?&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Eight Causes of Earthquakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
And the Venerable Ananda approached the Blessed One, and respectfully greeting him, sat down at one side. Then he spoke to the Blessed One, saying: &quot;Marvellous it is indeed, and most wonderful! The earth shakes mightily, tremendously! Dreadful and astonishing it is how the thunders roll across the heavens! What could be the reason, what the cause, that so mighty an earthquake should arise?&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Then the Blessed One said: &quot;There are eight reasons, Ananda, eight causes for a mighty earthquake to arise. What are those eight?

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &quot;This great earth, Ananda, is established upon liquid, the liquid upon the atmosphere, and the atmosphere upon space. And when, Ananda, mighty atmospheric disturbances take place, the liquid is agitated. And with the agitation of the liquid, tremors of the earth arise. This is the first reason, the first cause for the arising of mighty earthquakes.

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &quot;Again, Ananda, when an ascetic or holy man of great power, one who has gained mastery of his mind, or a deity who is mighty and potent, develops intense concentration on the delimited aspect of the earth element, and to a boundless degree on the liquid element, he, too, causes the earth to tremble, quiver, and shake. This is the second reason, the second cause for the arising of mighty earthquakes.

&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;no-bullet&quot;&gt;

&lt;li&gt;16-21. &quot;Again, Ananda, when the Bodhisatta departs from the Tusita realm and descends into his mother&#39;s womb, mindfully and clearly comprehending; and when the Bodhisatta comes out from his mother&#39;s womb, mindfully and clearly comprehending; and when the Tathagata becomes fully enlightened in unsurpassed, supreme Enlightenment; when the Tathagata sets rolling the excellent Wheel of the Dhamma; when the Tathagata renounces his will to live on; and when the Tathagata comes to pass away into the state of Nibbana in which no element of clinging remains — then, too, Ananda, this great earth trembles, quivers, and shakes.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;These, Ananda, are the eight reasons, the eight causes for a great earthquake to arise. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:27&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:27&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mara&#39;s Former Temptation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;li&gt;42. &quot;There was a time, Ananda, when I dwelt at Uruvela, on the bank of the Nerañjara River, at the foot of the goatherds&#39; banyan-tree, soon after my supreme Enlightenment. And Mara, the Evil One, approached me, saying: &#39;Now, O Lord, let the Blessed One come to his final passing away! Let the Happy One utterly pass away! The time has come for the Parinibbana of the Lord.&#39;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
43. &quot;Then, Ananda, I answered Mara, the Evil One, saying: &#39;I shall not come to my final passing away, Evil One, until my bhikkhus and bhikkhunis, laymen and laywomen, have come to be true disciples — wise, well disciplined, apt and learned, preservers of the Dhamma, living according to the Dhamma, abiding by appropriate conduct and, having learned the Master&#39;s word, are able to expound it, preach it, proclaim it, establish it, reveal it, explain it in detail, and make it clear; until, when adverse opinions arise, they shall be able to refute them thoroughly and well, and to preach this convincing and liberating Dhamma.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
44. &quot;&#39;I shall not come to my final passing away, Evil One, until this holy life taught by me has become successful, prosperous, far-renowned, popular, and widespread, until it is well proclaimed among gods and men.&#39;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
45. &quot;And again today, Ananda, at the Capala shrine, Mara, the Evil One, approached me, saying: &#39;Now, O Lord, bhikkhus and bhikkhunis, laymen and laywomen, have come to be true disciples of the Blessed One — wise, well disciplined, apt and learned, preservers of the Dhamma, living according to the Dhamma, abiding in the appropriate conduct, and having learned the Master&#39;s word, are able to expound it, preach it, proclaim it, establish it, reveal it, explain it in detail, and make it clear; and when adverse opinions arise, they are now able to refute them thoroughly and well, and to preach this convincing and liberating Dhamma.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;&#39;And now, O Lord, this holy life taught by the Blessed One has become successful, prosperous, far-renowned, popular and widespread, and it is well proclaimed among gods and men. Therefore, O Lord, let the Blessed One come to his final passing away! Let the Happy One utterly pass away! The time has come for the Parinibbana of the Lord.&#39;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
46. &quot;And then, Ananda, I answered Mara, the Evil One, saying: &#39;Do not trouble yourself, Evil One. Before long the Parinibbana of the Tathagata will come about. Three months hence the Tathagata will utterly pass away.&#39;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
47. And in this way, Ananda, today at the Capala shrine the Tathagata has renounced his will to live on
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ananda&#39;s Appeal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
48. At these words the Venerable Ananda spoke to the Blessed One, saying: &quot;May the Blessed One remain, O Lord! May the Happy One remain, O Lord, throughout the world-period, for the welfare and happiness of the multitude, out of compassion for the world, for the benefit, well being, and happiness of gods and men!&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
49. And the Blessed One answered, saying: &quot;Enough, Ananda. Do not entreat the Tathagata, for the time is past, Ananda, for such an entreaty.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
50-51. But for a second and a third time, the Venerable Ananda said to the Blessed One: &quot;May the Blessed One remain, O Lord! May the Happy One remain, O Lord, throughout the world-period, for the welfare and happiness of the multitude, out of compassion for the world, for the benefit, well being, and happiness of gods and men!&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
52. Then the Blessed One said: &quot;Do you have faith, Ananda, in the Enlightenment of the Tathagata?&quot; And the Venerable Ananda replied: &quot;Yes, O Lord, I do.&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Then how, Ananda, can you persist against the Tathagata even up to the third time?&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
53. Then the Venerable Ananda said: &quot;This, O Lord, I have heard and learned from the Blessed One himself when the Blessed One said to me: &#39;Whosoever, Ananda, has developed, practiced, employed, strengthened, maintained, scrutinized, and brought to perfection the four constituents of psychic power could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it. The Tathagata, Ananda, has done so. Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.&#39;&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
54. &quot;And did you believe it, Ananda?&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Yes, O Lord, I did.&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Then, Ananda, the fault is yours. Herein have you failed, inasmuch as you were unable to grasp the plain suggestion, the significant prompting given by the Tathagata, and you did not then entreat the Tathagata to remain. For if you had done so, Ananda, twice the Tathagata might have declined, but the third time he would have consented. Therefore, Ananda, the fault is yours; herein have you failed.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
55. &quot;At Rajagaha, Ananda, when dwelling at Vultures&#39; Peak, I spoke to you, saying: &#39;Pleasant, Ananda, is Rajagaha; pleasant is Vultures&#39; Peak. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.&#39;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
56. &quot;So also at the Banyan Grove, at Robbers&#39; Cliff, at the Sattapanni Cave on the Vebhara Mountain, at the Black Rock of Isigili, at the Serpents&#39; Pool in the Cool Forest, at the Tapoda Grove, at the Bamboo Grove in the Squirrels&#39; Feeding-ground, at Jivaka&#39;s Mango Grove, and at Small Nook in the Deer Park I spoke to you in the same words, saying: &#39;Pleasant, Ananda, is Rajagaha, pleasant are these places. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.&#39;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;But you, Ananda, were unable to grasp the plain suggestion, the significant prompting given you by the Tathagata, and you did not entreat the Tathagata to remain. For if you had done so, Ananda, twice the Tathagata might have declined, but the third time he would have consented. Therefore, Ananda, the fault is yours; herein you have failed.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
57. &quot;So also at Vesali, Ananda, at different times the Tathagata has spoken to you, saying: &#39;Pleasant, Ananda, is Vesali; pleasant are the shrines of Udena, Gotamaka, Sattambaka, Bahuputta, Sarandada, and Capala. Whosoever, Ananda, has developed... Therefore the Tathagata could, if he so desired, remain throughout a world-period or until the end of it.&#39;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;But you, Ananda, were unable to grasp the plain suggestion, the significant prompting, given you by the Tathagata, and you did not entreat the Tathagata to remain. For if you had done so, Ananda, twice the Tathagata might have declined, but the third time he would have consented. Therefore, Ananda, the fault is yours; herein you have failed.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
58. &quot;Yet, Ananda, have I not taught from the very beginning that with all that is dear and beloved there must be change, separation, and severance? Of that which is born, come into being, is compounded and subject to decay, how can one say: &#39;May it not come to dissolution!&#39; There can be no such state of things. And of that, Ananda, which the Tathagata has finished with, that which he has relinquished, given up, abandoned, and rejected — his will to live on — the Tathagata&#39;s word has been spoken once for all: &#39;Before long the Parinibbana of the Tathagata will come about. Three months hence the Tathagata will utterly pass away.&#39; And that the Tathagata should withdraw his words for the sake of living on — this is an impossibility.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Last Admonition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
59. &quot;So, then, Ananda, let us go to the hall of the Gabled House, in the Great Forest.&quot; And the Venerable Ananda replied: &quot;So be it, Lord.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
60. Then the Blessed One, with the Venerable Ananda, went to the hall of the Gabled House, in the Great Forest. And there he spoke to the Venerable Ananda, saying: &quot;Go now, Ananda, and assemble in the hall of audience all the bhikkhus who dwell in the neighborhood of Vesali.&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;So be it, Lord.&quot; And the Venerable Ananda gathered all the bhikkhus who dwelt in the neighborhood of Vesali, and assembled them in the hall of audience. And then, respectfully saluting the Blessed One, and standing at one side, he said: &quot;The community of bhikkhus is assembled, Lord. Now let the Blessed One do as he wishes.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
61. Thereupon the Blessed One entered the hall of audience, and taking the seat prepared for him, he exhorted the bhikkhus, saying: &quot;Now, O bhikkhus, I say to you that these teachings of which I have direct knowledge and which I have made known to you — these you should thoroughly learn, cultivate, develop, and frequently practice, that the life of purity may be established and may long endure, for the welfare and happiness of the multitude, out of compassion for the world, for the benefit, well being, and happiness of gods and men.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
62. &quot;And what, bhikkhus, are these teachings? They are the four foundations of mindfulness, the four right efforts, the four constituents of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven factors of enlightenment, and the Noble Eightfold Path. These, bhikkhus, are the teachings of which I have direct knowledge, which I have made known to you, and which you should thoroughly learn, cultivate, develop, and frequently practice, that the life of purity may be established and may long endure, for the welfare and happiness of the multitude, out of compassion for the world, for the benefit, well being, and happiness of gods and men.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
63. Then the Blessed One said to the bhikkhus: &quot;So, bhikkhus, I exhort you: All compounded things are subject to vanish. Strive with earnestness. The time of the Tathagata&#39;s Parinibbana is near. Three months hence the Tathagata will utterly pass away.&quot;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
64. And having spoken these words, the Happy One, the Master, spoke again, saying:
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;My years are now full ripe, the life span left is short.
Departing, I go hence from you, relying on myself alone.
Be earnest, then, O bhikkhus, be mindful and of virtue pure!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With firm resolve, guard your own mind!
Whoso untiringly pursues the Dhamma and the Discipline
Shall go beyond the round of births and make an end of suffering.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;ul class=&quot;no-bullet&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;21. &lt;i&gt;Kappam va tittheyya kappavasesam va.&lt;/i&gt; Comy. takes &lt;i&gt;kappa&lt;/i&gt; not as &quot;world-period&quot; or &quot;aeon,&quot; but as &lt;i&gt;ayu-kappa,&lt;/i&gt; &quot;life span,&quot; and explains &lt;i&gt;avasesa&lt;/i&gt; (usually &quot;remainder&quot;) by &quot;in excess.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comy.: &quot;He may stay alive completing the life span pertaining to men at the given time. (Sub. Comy.: the maximum life span.) &lt;i&gt;Kappavasesa:&lt;/i&gt; &#39;in excess&#39; &lt;i&gt;(atireka),&lt;/i&gt; i.e., more or less above the hundred years said to be the normally highest life expectation.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Among the numerous meanings of the word &lt;i&gt;kappa,&lt;/i&gt; there is, in fact, that of time in general &lt;i&gt;(kala)&lt;/i&gt; and not only the duration of an aeon; but the meaning &quot;life span&quot; seems to have been ascribed to it only in this passage. Also, the meaning &quot;in excess&quot; for &lt;i&gt;avasesa&lt;/i&gt; (usually &quot;remainder&quot;) is unusual.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The four constituents of psychic power &lt;i&gt;(iddhipada)&lt;/i&gt; are concentration due to zeal, energy, purity of mind, and investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
     &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;22. According to Comy., Ananda&#39;s mind had been influenced &lt;i&gt;(pariyutthitacitto)&lt;/i&gt; by Mara&#39;s exhibiting a frightful sight which distracted his attention, preventing him from grasping the Buddha&#39;s suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;23. &quot;Convincing and liberating.&quot; This stands for the one Pali word &lt;i&gt;sappatihariya,&lt;/i&gt; an attempt to render the two connotations which the word has according to the commentaries and in the context of other occurrences in the Canon. The commentaries derive it from the verb &lt;i&gt;patiharati,&lt;/i&gt; &quot;to remove,&quot; and explain it as (1) the removal of what is adverse, e.g., opposition and objections (covered by &quot;convincing&quot;), and (2) the removal of inner obstructions, i.e., defilements such as greed, etc., effected by arahatship. It is probably to point to that latter meaning that the commentary to our present text paraphrases our passage as follows: &quot;until they are able to preach the Teaching in its liberating &lt;i&gt;(niyyanika)&lt;/i&gt; capacity.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;24. &lt;i&gt;Tulam atulañca sambhavam:&lt;/i&gt; lit. &quot;the measurable and immeasurable productive cause (of life),&quot; i.e., the volitional action causing rebirth in the confined, or limited sense-sphere, or in the unbounded fine-material and immaterial spheres.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;25. &lt;i&gt;Bhavasankhara:&lt;/i&gt; the formative force of becoming, in the sense of what forms existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn:26&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;26. &lt;i&gt;Kavacam iv&#39;attasambhavam.&lt;/i&gt; Comy.: &quot;He breaks through the entire net of defilements that envelops individual existence like a coat of mail; he breaks the defilements as a great warrior breaks his armor after a battle.&quot; The Sanskrit version has &quot;like an egg shell&quot; &lt;i&gt;(kosam iv&#39; anda-sambhavam).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:26&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&quot;fn:27&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;27. Comy.: &quot;Even by this much the Venerable Ananda was aware of the fact: &#39;Surely, today the Blessed One has renounced his will to live on.&#39; Though the Blessed One knew that the Venerable Ananda was aware of it, he did not give him another opportunity to ask him to stay on for the remainder of his life span, but he spoke to him about other eight-term groups beginning with the eight assemblies.&quot; Sub. Comy.: &quot;Some say that the Buddha did so in order to divert the Venerable Ananda and to prevent grief from arising in him.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:27&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

]]></description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 20:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2013/04/04/maha-parinibbana-sutta-relinquishing-the-will-to-live/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2013/04/04/maha-parinibbana-sutta-relinquishing-the-will-to-live/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Sister Vajira &amp; Francis Story</dc:creator>
        
        <dc:source>http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/dn/dn.16.1-6.vaji.html</dc:source>
        
      </item>
      
    
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Finding the right question (how to solve problems creatively)</title>
        <description><![CDATA[&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-problem&quot;&gt;What is the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birth is a problem, aging is a problem, dying is a problem.
Not getting what you want is a problem. Having what you don’t want is a problem. Not attaining one’s ambitions is a problem.
Believing in your sense of identity is a problem.
And the origin of problems is therefore desire – sense desire, meaning the desire to get something you haven’t got, or the desire to get rid of something; and becoming, that is the desire to become someone you aren’t or the desire to cease being someone.
Can all your problems be captured in this model?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your happiness depend on having problems? It is a way we can express our identity – I am a person who ……has a problem.
My problem is ….
My problem is I care too much – and you don’t care enough.
My problem is that my husband is expecting me to act as if nothing has happened.
My problem is I’m too good.
My problem is I can’t ……
My problem is, I’m not happy if I haven’t got a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanting to solve problems is just another desire. The best bit is when you know you have the solution, but you haven’t tried it out yet. When you put it into practice, you realise it wasn’t the solution after all – but the moment when you have the solution but haven’t actually tried it out is bliss. Just like having anything you desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorting out problems can happen two ways – one is with greed, hatred and delusion and one is without. One creates more problems and the other brings them to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-the-right-question&quot;&gt;Finding the right question.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take a problem you have – something relatively trivial is good – try finding the solution for one minute – really one minute. Now what did you discover? How realistic was the solution?
For example - My problem is … I have too much work to do and I must get it done this morning. The solution which presents itself is to get into a mad panic and start rushing at everything at once to get it all finished.
Now spend one minute thinking of the right question – in this example, I let go of any idea of a solution immediately. I realise I have more important things to do than solve this problem – like washing up, and I need a shave. The work I have to do will wait. The jobs are better done one at a time in an ordered way, and even if I do just one thing on my list, I will have achieved something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the right question? For a Buddhist it is ‘who?’ Because what we learn from our practice is that we create problems through self identity. If we take the ‘I am’ out of them they are revealed for what they are – as self created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the examples of problems I gave and you can see the self which is behind them. Now look at your own problems – can you see the same thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-ultimately-there-are-no-problems-yet-our-lives-are-full-of-them&quot;&gt;So ultimately there are no problems. Yet our lives are full of them.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what we need to do now, and doing it, is the art of living.
Problems arise because we don’t know how to act with wisdom when we need to. Because we didn’t know how to act skilfully in the past, we live in difficult relationships and difficult situations in the present.
How do we change these relationships / situations? Not through following our desire for them to be different, or our aversion to how they are. First we have to accept them as they are and accept our part in creating them this way – and forgive ourselves and others. Then we can start from the right place, back at the beginning. Go back to the time it first went wrong – how could you have behaved differently? Now you have a key to changing the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
]]></description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2012 16:50:47 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2012/04/07/finding-the-right-question/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.bodhinyanagroup.org.uk/2012/04/07/finding-the-right-question/</guid>
        
        
        <dc:creator>Martin Evans</dc:creator>
        
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
